Today we're going to
discuss algorithms for
answering questions about
regular languages, or
really about the representations for
the languages, such as finite automata.
The questions that we can resolve for
finite automata include many we cannot
resolve for programs in general.
Examples include whether a given string
is accepted by a given automata.
That's the membership problem.
Or whether a given automaton
accepts any string at all.
The emptiness problem.
As part of our discussion, we're going
to prove an important theorem called
the Pumping Lemma that let's us show
certain languages not to be regular.
Automata theory talks about many different
classes of languages including context
free languages, recursive, and
recursively innumerable languages.
We're going to meet each of these classes,
but
for the moment we know only one class,
the regular languages.
When we investigate a class of
languages they're two important issues.
The first is decision properties.
Which we'll see that there are many
questions we might like to ask about
a language, or
rather its representation such at
whether it is empty finite or infinite.
It's good to know there are algorithms
to answer such questions at least for
the regular languages.
Unfortunately as we meet
larger classes of languages,
we find that in general the larger the
class of languages, the less likely there
is to be an algorithm to answer
question about languages in that class.
The second important issue is
closure properties of the class.
These involve applying operations such
as union to languages in the class.
We're going to defer the discussion of
closure properties to another lecture,
though I'll give you
an example on the next slide.
Closure properties are statements that
when we apply certain operations to
languages in the class,
the result is also in the class.
For example, we say that a class of
languages is closed under union if, given
two languages in the class, the union of
those languages is also in the class.
So if I have two regular languages, I can
represent them by regular expressions, and
connect those expressions by a plus
with the appropriate parentheses,
to get a regular expression for
their union.
Similar constructions work for
their concatenation enclosure.
Now let us address the main
topic of this lecture,
decision properties of regular languages.
We've used both formal and
informal ways of describing languages.
The formal ways including finding
atomata and regular expressions,
each of which defines a language by
a precise mathematical definition.
But we've also described languages
informally by pro statements and
set formats such as this.
Or even more informal statements,
like this.
Okay.
However, you can't answer questions
about a language unless you have
a formal description.
For example, for instance we will talk
shortly about testing whether a regular
language is infinite,
given one of its formal representation.
It looks like the last of the informal
description describes an infinite set, but
does the word some mean any or
some, one particular number like 10,
for example, that I have in mind.
Thus we're only going to use formal
descriptions of languages when we
talk about algorithms, for
deciding things about those languages.
Thus a decision property for
class of languages is an algorithm that
takes a formal representative
of the language.
The algorithm answers some particular
question about the language,
such as whether or not the language
described by the representation is empty.
Here are a few examples of why we might
be interested in decision properties of
regular languages.
Both involve protocols
represented by automata.
If we ask whether the language's
section automaton is finite, we are in
effect asking whether the protocol it
represents is guaranteed to terminate.
Or if we make the final state of the
automaton the error state, then asking if
it's language is empty is tantamount to
asking whether the protocol can fail.
And remember, we couldn't answer either of
these questions about programs in general,
so we couldn't get the answers to these
questions about protocols by looking at
the code that implements them.
Another use for
decision properties of regular languages
involves minimizing the representations.
For instance,
DFAs are a good representation for
certain kinds of digital circuits,
those that have memory.
We usually want the smallest
circuit to accomplish a task and
a good first step is to find
a DFA that does what we want and
has the smallest number of states
of any DFA for the same language.
It turns out that we can tell
whether two DFA's are equivalent,
that is whether they
define the same language.
That lets us find a minimum state
DFA equivalent to any given DFA.
Again, we can do none of this
with programs in general.
We can't tell whether two
programs do the same thing, and
we can't find a smallest equivalent for
a given program, even though we know
in principle that one must exist.
The membership question for regular
language is answered by an algorithm that
takes a DFA in a string and tells whether
or not the strings accepted by the DFA.
The algorithm is the obvious one.
Simulate the DFA on the input [SOUND],
okay.
Here's an example it's something
we've seen several times before.
Each time I show it to you, I use
a different style of presentation but
the idea is always the same.
Here it's the DFA for
strings without consecutive ones,uh,
something which I know we've seen before.
And the input string is 01011.
That obviously has consecutive ones so
it shouldn't be accepted.
Well let's see what happens
when we simulate it.
Read a zero stay in A.
When we read a one we go to B.
We read zero, we go back to A.
Read a one we go to B.
Read another one we go to C.
When we simulate this DFA on the input we
see that in D the string gets the state C,
and it is not accepted.
Now you might wonder what if
the regular language were
represented by an NFA or
a regular expression for example.
Then you first need to convert
the representation to a DFA, and
then simulate the DFA.
It is possible to convert from any of
the four representations we know about
to any of the others using
this circle of conversions.
So doing might exponentiate
the size of the description but
there's still an algorithm
to do the conversion.
And that's all we need
to show there is for
example an algorithm to tell
given a regular expression and
a string, whether the string is in
the language of the regular expression.
Generally, proofs the closure or
decision properties require either a DFA
or a regular expression by the way.
The emptiness problem is
given a representation for
a regular language, does it's
language contain any string at all?
Okay, we're going to assume
language is represented by DFA.
Obviously if by some other representation,
then convert it to a DFA.
Finding reachable states
requires a breadth first or
depth first search from the start state.
I'm not going to assume you are familiar
with these search techniques, but
it is fairly easy to think of some way of
searching a graph from a single node by
following all arch are nodes and
markings those nodes are to visited.
Then, follow archs under
the nodes you visited and
mark any other notes you visit.
Keep doing that until you
cannot mark any other nodes.
The mark nodes are those that are reached
from the start estate on some input,
if at least one final state is marked and
the DFA accepted at least one input.
If no final state is marked,
then it isn't possible for
the DFA to accept anything
in it's language empty.
Here is an example here, here's your
start state we might mark, mark it.
Mark these guys,
maybe mark these guys as we go.
But if all your final states
are out here and never get marked.
Then obviously no matter how
complex this automaton is
you can't reach your final state and
you can't accept anything.
Now if you have an automaton
with three states,
it's pretty easy to tell what's
reachable and what isn't.
But if you have a million states
represented by some table,
then it hardly easy to tell.
But fortunately we have a straightforward
search algorithm regardless how
large the automaton or graph is.
Now let us take up a more difficult
problem, but one that we can still solve.
We'd like to know whether or
not the language defined by
DFA is finite or infinite.
The first fact we're going to prove, is
that if the language of the DFA contains
any string of length n or more where n
is the number of the states the DFA.
Then the DFA contains
an infinite number of strings.
Surely if DFA doesn't accept any string
of length equal to or greater than n and
exceptionally finite number of strings.
However, it doesn't seem feasible
to test membership roll and
push string's length and more, since
there are an infinite number of them.
Can we ever finish?
If not, then we really don't have
an algorithm for testing infiniteness.
But as we shall see, it is possible
to limit the length of strings we
have to test to twice
the number of states.
So we have a really large and ugly but
finite task, and
we really do have an algorithm.
So lets try to prove the point we need.
That if DFA accepts any string who's
length is at least the number of states n,
that an accepted infinite
number of strings.
First observe that a string of length n or
more has at least n plus
1 states along this path.
For example, a string of length
two has three states on it's.
It's path here is a typical
picture we might have.
String ab looks like that.
Notice no matter how many, well,
the number of symbols in
the string is the number of.
Arcs, and there's always one more
node than there are arcs in the path.
That's why, there will be,
n plus 1 states, for a string of length n.
Now, if there are only n different states,
and there are n plus one
states along the path.
Then two states along
the path must be the same.
That's called the pigeonhole principle,
you might remember.
Here's a picture of the path for
string w, which we're breaking up as xyz.
X is the prefix of w that gets the DFA to
the first state that repeats on the path,
which we call state q,
right here of course.
Then y is a part of w that gets
the DFA back to q for the first time.
That is the end of y is
the second occurrence of q.
Notice that therefore y cannot be the
empty string, although x or z might be.
Finally, z is the rest of w when we
know it gets the DFA to a final state,
because w is accepted by the DFA.
Notice that the path labelled z may have
states that also appear earlier, but
it doesn't matter.
The important thing is that we
identify the first repeating state, q.
The claim that x followed by i
repetitions of y followed by z
is also accepted by the DFA for
any integer i.
To see y, x takes us to state q so
for example go like this.
Okay, and then we could skip y altogether,
just follow z and
we get to a final state that tells
us that xz is in the language.
Or, we could follow x to state q,
we could go around loops many, many times,
and then finally go off following z,
and again get to the final sate.
Or, after i, use of input y for
any i, however large,
we follow input z and we accept.
This proves that xy to the iz
is accepted for any i.
Remember that y cannot be empty, so
all these excepted strings are different,
thus the DFA accept an infinite
number of strings, one for each i.
Remember, we still do not have
an algorithm because we can't test
the infinite number of strings at
length equal to or greater than n.
However, we don't have to.
Because it is sufficient to test strings
of length between n and 2n minus one.
And there are a finite
number of such strings.
When we prove the state, well, we should
at least have an algorithm although it is
a rather time consuming one.
Now we picked y to be the first
cycle on the path, so
the length of xy cannot be greater than n.
That is some state within the first n plus
1 states on the path, surely repeats.
We also know that if length of y is at
least one, so y lies between one and n.
Then if w is the shortest accepted
string of length at least n,
then we,
claim that w cannot be as long as 2n.
For suppose it were?
Now, xz as we know,
is another accepted string.
And the length of xz is the length
of w minus the length of y.
And the length of y is at most n.
So the length of xz is at least n.
That means that xz is
a string shorter that double,
but at least n in length,
and it's also accepted.
But we assume that there was no strings
accepted that were shorter than w and
also of length at least n.
As a result, given any really long string
w that's accepted we can keep taking out
pieces of length between one and n, that's
the y in each of these, the diagrams.
And we just keep throwing them away and
eventually what's left of w will
be between n and 2n minus one.
So the algorithm to decide whether
a regular language is infinite is to
construct a DFA for it and
let the DFA have end states.
Test all the strings of length
between n and 2n minus one and
say infinite if any of them are accepted.
Otherwise say finite.
This is a terrible algorithm.
If there are k input symbols in end states
then the number of strings we have to
simulate is about k to the power 2n.
That is a lot of work and
there's a much more efficient algorithm.
Algorithm, one that takes time
proportional to the number of transitions,
that is, k times n, if implemented right.
I wanted to give you the argument
about the lengths of strings,
because it's important when we take
up the pumping lemma, a technique for
showing languages not to be regular.
However, let's sketch how
the efficient algorithm will.
We already discussed searching
forward from a node in a graph to
find all the nodes you can reach.
So we can eliminate the states not
reachable from the start state.
We then want to eliminate states
that don't reach a final state.
This algorithm is the same except
start by marking the final states and
follow the arcs backwards.
Now there's an elegant algorithm for
finding cycles using depth-first search
that takes time proportional to
the number of edges or transitions.
I'm going to trust that you'll meet this
algorithm in a course on algorithms if
a data structure.
If you haven't already done so.
However here's a simple way to test for
a cycle in a graph.
It takes time proportional
to the number of nodes or
states times the number of arcs or
transitions.
We're going to do the same thing for
each node n.
Starting at n search forward until
you either can reach no more nodes.
Or you discover that you can reach in,
that is, here's node n,
we explore forward from it.
And if we're lucky, at some point, we,
we reach a node that has an R back to n.
Okay.
If you can reach n,
then you have a cycle and
you conclude the language
of the DFA is infinite.
If not,
try the same process from another node.
If you exhaust all the nodes or starting
points and you still haven't found
a cycle, then there are none and
you conclude the language is finite.
This is a good time to
introduce the pumping lemma for
regular languages because we have
essentially proved it during our
analysis of the infiniteness problem.
Here is the statement
of the pumping lemma.
For every regular language
L there is is an integer n,
which happens to be number of states for
some DFA for
L, such that every string w in
L whose link is at least n.
We can break w into w equals xyz,
where y is the label of
the first substring of
wthat goes from the state to the same
state, as we saw on the previous slide,
such that the three things are true First,
the prefix of xy of w is short,.
It is of length at most n.
We assure that by making y be the label
of the first cycle we encounter.
Second, y is not the empty string.
We assure this because y connects
two different occurrences of
the same state along the same of w.
And lastly x z is in L for all integers i.
The statement is particularly complex,
because it is in the form for
all there exists, for all there exists.
But here's how we use it.
Think of game played between you and
an advisory.
You pick the language L that you
want to show is not regular, and
suppose the advisory claims it is regular.
Then the advisory has to provide that
their exist parts while you play the for
all parts.
You've already picked L, now the advisory
has to pick n, he can pick a number as
large as he likes but once picked it
is finalized and the game proceeds.
Now you get to pick the string w
subject only to the constraint that
is at least as long as n.
Then the number that the advisory picked.
Next the advisory has to break your w up
into xyz, subject to the constraint that
the length of xy is at most n, and
the length of y is at least one.
You win the game by picking an i
such that xy to the iz is not in L.
However, in a proof, we don't know
what moves the adversary will make.
Thus to win,
we need to cover all possible moves.
That is, we know the picked n but
we don't know n's actual value so
we must pick w in terms of n.
Similarly, we know w equals xyz but
we don't know exactly where
y is except that it is not empty, and
it is among the first n positions of w.
Thus our argument that xy to the iz
is not an incomplete work for
any of these possible y's.
Now, let's see an example.
Let us pick this language as L.
It is the set of strings
consisting of some number of
zeros followed with
the same number of ones.
And we've claimed before that it is
an example of a non regular language.
Now we're going to prove it.
Now the advisory picks n,
we don't know what n is, but
we know it has some fixed value.
Now we get to choose w in terms of n,
and we pick w equals zero to the n one.
That is n zeroes follwed by n ones.
But then the advisory gets
to break w into x, y, z, and
we don't know exactly how it is broken.
But we know enough about xyz to show that
there is some string, in particular,
the case i equals two, that the pumping
lemma says has to be in the language L.
But obviously it isn't because
it has more zeros than ones.
That is, we know that y,
being part of the first n positions of w,
can have only zeros.
Okay, so two y's, have more,
zeros than one y.
And the number of oness, which are all
contained within z, doesn't change.
We next take up a question of
testing whether two regular
languages are the same.
We suppose we are given representations
for two languages L and M.
Whatever representation we're given,
we convert to DFAs, and
then we have to combine those
DFAs into a single DFA,
that in a sense that runs both
of those DFAs in parallel.
We call it the product DFA.
Suppose these two DFAs have states,
q and r.
In the product DFA, the states of pair
as one state from Q, the other from R.
The start state of the product
DFA is the pair consisting of
the start state from each DFA.
For the transitions of the product DFA,
suppose we have a state
that is the pair of q,r?
And suppose A is the input symbol for
which we want to figure
out the transition.
We look at the transition function for
the first DFA, say delta L.
And we see where q goes on input A.
So here's q, and on input A,
it goes to some state like that.
Then we look at the transition function
for the second DFA, say delta M, and
we see where r goes on input A.
So here's r on input A,
it goes somewhere here.
Then in the product DFA,
the transition from the state
QR on input A is the state pair.
That is the first component is delta,
the L of QA, and
who's second component is delta M of RA.
That is we stimulate the two
transitions in parallel.
Here's a little example.
Here are the two given DFAs.
Call this the orange DFA,
and that the purple DFA.
And here's the product DFA.
It's here.
For example let's figure out
the transition from A, C, on zero.
So here's state A, C.
And I look in the orange automaton,
A out of zero goes to A itself.
And in the purple automaton,
C on a zero goes to D.
So the combination AC goes to AD,
and you see that transition here.
For another example,
where does AD go on input one?
Well, the orange automaton
says A goes to B on one,
and the purple automaton
says D goes to C on one,
so on one, AD goes to BC.
That's this transition there.
The algorithm for testing whether
testing to DFAs are equivalent,
that is whether they accept the language,
begins by constructing the product DFA.
Make the final states with the product
DFA be all those pairs such that
one is a final stage and the other isn't.
Extreme w reaches one of these
final states in the product.
And w is accepted by one of
the original DFAs and not the other.
Thus the two languages are not the same.
Only if the product DFA with this
selection of final states has
an empty language
are the two DFAs equivalent.
Here's an example.
A,C is made a final state because
in the original automaton,
C is final and A is not.
Likewise, BD is final because
B is final but D is not.
We now see that the two original
DFAs are not equivalent.
It happens that the final state BD is
not reachable from the start state.
So there are no strings that
the orange automaton accepts but
the purple one does not.
However, AC is also a final state and
it is obviously reachable from the start
state because it is the start state.
That is, the empty string distinguishes
from between the two automata.
The empty string is accepted by the orange
automaton but not the purple one.
A related question to ask
about regular languages is,
is whether one is
contained than the other.
[SOUND] The test is in a sense one half
of the equivalence test we just saw.
Start by building the product automaton.
[SOUND] But we have to define
the final states differently.
How would you do that?
That is, L is not contained in M if, and
only if,
some string w that is in L is not in M.
Such a string would get the DFA for
L to a final state, but
would not get the DFA for
M to a final state.
So the question of containment
is the same as the question of
whether there is any string w that gets
the product automaton to a state, q,r,
where q is final and r is not.
Here, b is the only final state
of the first automaton and
d is the only non-final state
of the second automaton.
So only b,d is final.
As we ob, as we observed before b,
d is not reachable from the start state.
It has arcs out but not arcs in.
Thus the language of the product
automaton is empty, and
we conclude that the language of
the orange automaton is a subset of.
Of the line between the purple atomata.
Next we're going to attack
the problem of given DFA,
find the equivalent DFA
with the fewest states.
There is an obvious dumb algorithm,
just consider all the DFAs with
the same input alphabet but
a smaller number of states.
There is a huge but
finite number of such automata.
So in principle we can solve this problem.
This time we're not going to
dwell on the bad algorithm.
We'll talk you through the good
algorithm immediately.
The key idea is to build
a table of pairs of states and
figure out which pairs
are distinguishable.
In the sense that there is some input
string that leads one of the pair to
a final state and
the other two are non final state.
Otherwise state indistinguishable and
they can be conversed to a single state.
Here's the tennis of automata,
we saw way back the beginning course
now let's look at the states for
40-30 and Ad-in.
Input S takes them both to an accepting
state that is Server Wins, and
input O takes them both to deuce,
here and here.
Thus no further inputs could ever
distinguish 40-30 from Ad-in.
Similarly 30-40 and
Ad-out are indistinguishable.
Now we can deduce that 30-all, here.
And deuce are also
indistinguishable on input S.
They go to 40-30 and Ad-in,
respectively, that is here 30-all,
goes to 40-30 on S, and
deuce goes to Ad-in on, on S.
But we know that those two
states are indistinguishable.
So we'll never be able to
distinguish 30-all from
deuce by a sequence beginning with S.
And further on input O,
well 30-all goes to 30-40,
and deuce goes to Ad-out.
And we said we can't
distinguish these two states.
So there's no string whatsoever that
can distinguish 30-all from deuce.
'Kay, we're now going to talk about how
we find the distinguishable states.
The basis is pairs that
are distinguishable by the empty string.
These are the pairs that have one
final and one non-final state.
For the inductive step we can mark
a pair q,r if these states go at some
input to distinguishable states.
That is say here is q and
an a goes to some state.
I don't know what it is, but
it's certainly delta of q and a.
And here's r, and it goes on a,
to, again, some other state.
I don't know what it is,
but it's delta of r and a.
And then these two states on input
w will say that this one goes to
a non-final state, and
that goes to a final state on input w.
'Kay, then I claim a,w distinguishes
q from r because obviously
q goes on aw to a non final state and
r goes on the same a,w to a final state.
After no more marks are possible,
the unmarked pairs are equivalent.
And can be merged into one state.
This point may be obvious, but
we're going to to need it and one follows.
If there's no string w that
distinguishes state p, states p and q,
and there is no string that
distinguishes q from r,
then how could some string
w distinguish p from r?
That would mean that there's some
string w means one of p and r,
to a final state and
the other two in non-final state.
Let's say r leads to a final state, so
here's w leading p to
a non-final state and here's r.
And on the same w, gets to a final state.
But then w,
also distinguishes q from either p or r.
So here's q, and w,
leads it to some state.
Okay, so let's say that w,
leads q to a final state.
And w distinguishes q from p because
your p on w goes to a non-final state,
q on w goes to a final state.
Okay?
If q goes to a non-final state,
then it doesn't distinguish p from q.
But it does distinguish r from q.
Because q will then go [INAUDIBLE]
non-final state while r
goes to a final state.
Incidentally, distinguishable
is not transitive.
It is quite possible that w distinguishes
p from q and also q from r.
But does not distinguish p from r.
For example w could lead both p and r to
final states, and q to a non-final state.
We're now going to use the table
of indistinguishabliliy to
merge states are indistinguishable.
That gives us the minimum state DFA,
although we must be carefully to remove at
some stage, all the states that are not
reachable from the start state.
Suppose we have a set of indistinguishable
states, say q-1 through q-k.
We're going to replace them all by a
single state that behaves as they all do.
Call the representative q.
It can be one of the qi's or
some new name we create for this purpose.
On any symbol a, all
the indistinguishable states, the qi's,
go to states that are also
indistinguishable from one another.
For if not then we could use a distinction
between, say, the states delta q1 of a and
delta of q2 of a to
distinguish between q1 and q2.
But we already know that q1 and q2 are
indistinguishable so that can't happen.
Thus make the transition for state q
on input a, be the representative for
the indistinguishable states delta q1 a,
and so on.
Let's work with the DFA that we
constructed from the NFA that
represented moves on a chessboard.
We're going to make it easier to
work with by renaming the states to
be single letters.
For example,
A is the set containing only one.
And G is the set containing one,
three, five, seven, and nine.
Here's a little trick for
arranging pairs in a triangle, so
each pair appears exactly once.
Notice that the rows of
the states in order, except for
the last state, G,
which doesn't appear there.
There, then the columns are labelled by
the states in backwards order, except for
the first state, A.
We begin the table of
indistinguishabilities by marking each
pair that consists of a final state and
a non-final state.
Here the final states are F and G,
so pairs that have one of these and
one of the other states,
A through E, are marked.
Let's look at the transitions on input r.
Notice that the column for
r has only states b and d.
Since we have not yet distinguished
b from d, there's no way input r can
help distinguish other pairs
of states at this point.
However, we have more luck with input b.
Some states go to final states on input b,
mainly C, D, E and
G, and the others A B and
F go to nonfinal states.
Thus we can distinguish any of C,
D, E or G from any of A, B, or F.
Some of these pairs
are already distinguished but
we get seven new pairs marked in red here.
At the next step, we discovered two
more distinguishable pairs, C,D and C,E.
For example C and D lead to F and
Grespectively, on input B.
So we know that whatever string
w distinguishes F from G,
B followed by w will distinguish C from D.
Now we can mark the pair A,B.
These states transition
on input R to B and
D respectively, and we already
know we can distinguish B from D.
Unfortunately D and
E can never be marked because on both
inputs they go to the same state.
[SOUND] Okay.
We are now done,
we have distinguished every pair
of states except for D and E.
Moreover, we can never
distinguish these states,
since they both go to D on input r,
and to G on input B.
[SOUND] Thus, D and E form
an indistinguishable group of states,
and we can replace them
by a representative.
We choose the new state
H as the representative.
And all transitions from other states, the
D or E, are replaced by transitions to H.
The rows for D and
E are replaced by a row for H.
As D and E transition to D on input r,
H transitions to itself on r.
The transition on input B for H is to G,
which is the same as it was for
both D and E.
As we mentioned, collapsing
indistinguishable states to a single state
goes a long way to finding the
minimum-state equivalent to a given DFA.
But there is one other ratio that
indistinguishablility doesn't address,
the possible existence of unreachable
states that are cluttering up
the transition diagram or table.
But it is easy to find such states,
and we can either eliminate them from
the original DFA or we can eliminate them
after merging indistinguishable states.
It doesn't matter.
[SOUND] Now we're done our best to combine
states that we know how to combine.
[SOUND] But it is in principle
possible that there is some
other smaller DFA that we can't get
by combining states of our DFA.
[SOUND] And fortunately,
that can't happen, as we shall now see.
Here's the proof that there is
nothing smaller than the DFA we get by
merging states and
eliminating unreachable states.
Suppose A is our DFA, and B is a
hypothetical equivalent with fewer states.
Okay, imagine we combine the states
of A and B to form a larger DFA.
It doesn't matter what the start state
of the combined automaton is, but
the final states are those of A and B.
We need to use distinguishable in
its contrapositive form, that is.
If w distinguishes delta
of q,a from delta of p,a,
then surely a,w distinguishes q from p.
So if q and p are indistinguishable then
so are their successors on any input a.
[SOUND] Here's an informal
illustration of the proof technique.
We start off with the fact that
the start states of the time of A and
B are surely indistinguishable, because
the automata accept the same language.
Now suppose the start A go to
some states P and Q on input A.
P and Q must be indistinguishable,
because if they were distinguishable,
then we could distinguish the start
states, and we know we cannot do that.
Now, suppose q and
p go on input b to to other states,
r and s, then r and s must be
indistinguishable for the same reason.
Formerly we should prove that every state
q of A is indistinguishable from the som,
some state of B.
The proof is in induction on the length
of the shortest string that gets you to q
from A start state.
Notice that because we eliminated
unreasonable states we know there is
such a short string.
[SOUND] For bases the state of A that
is reachable from the start state
by string of length zero which is
of course the start state itself.
We know that this state of a is
indistinguishable from the start state
a to b because the languages are the same.
[SOUND] For the induction,
assume the inductive hypothesis for
strings shorter than w, and suppose w is
a shorter string getting A to state q.
Let w equal xa,
that is A is the last symbol of w, and.
X is all the rest of w.
We can plot the inductive hypothesis
to x because it is shorter than w.
You know, x gets a to some state r that is
indistinguishable from some state p of b.
But then,
a takes state r on input a to state q.
And we know B takes state p on input a,
to some state, say s.
And q must be indistinguishable from s,
using the argument that
we saw two slides ago.
Okay, now, we use the transistivity of
indistinguishable to argue that no two
states today, are in, indistinguishable
from the same state of B.
For, if they were, they would be
indistinguishable from each other.
But, we A,
can not have indistinguishable states,
because we merged them all constructing A.
Thus, B has at least as many states as A.
Even though we started off assuming
that there was no relationship between
automata A and B except that they
each accepted the same language.
So that concludes the, entire argument.
It says that,
by throwing away unreachable states and
then merging indistinguishable states
you get an automaton, that is a small,
that is, has as few states as any
other automaton for the same language.