There is a pumping lemma for
context free languages, analogous to
the pumping lemma for regular languages.
The goal of this lecture is to state and
prove this lemma, which is naturally more
complicated than the pumping lemma for
regular languages, and then use it to show
certain languages are not context free.
Let's review the pumping lemma for
regular languages.
It's said that any sufficiently long
string w, in a regular language,
has some short non-empty piece near
the beginning that we could pump.
That is, we could repeat it as many times
as we liked, including zero times, and
the resulting string would
also be in the language.
We found the string to pump by looking for
the first state to repeat, as a finite
automaton process, that's input w.
The pumping lemma for
context-free languages says that we
can find two pieces in any long string z,
and pump them in tandem.
That is,
we can repeat each of them I times for
any I greater than zero, and
the result will be in the same language.
We'll also see that these two
strings are close together in z, and
one can be empty but not both.
Here's the statement of the pumping
lemma for context-free languages.
We can see it as the same sort of
game with an adversary that we
talked about in connection
with regular languages.
For every context-free language L,
that is you get to pick L,
Presumably the one you want to
show isn't really context free.
There is an integer n.
This is something the adversary
gets to pick, but
once it's picked, it's fixed for
the rest of the game.
Such that for
every string z in L of length at least n.
And here you get to
pick the z to focus on.
You can break z into five pieces, u, v,
w, y, such that three things are true.
The adversary gets to
pick out z is broken, but
subject to two constraints
we'll see in just a moment.
And incidentally, v and
x are the sub strings that get pumped.
The first constraint is that the middle
three components, v, w,and x are short.
No longer than the length
of n put together.
Remember that V and X will get pumped.
So that says no only are they short, but
they appear within a bounded
distance from each other within z.
The second condition that
the adversary has to respect,
is that v and x cannot both be empty,
although one can.
And if all the above is satisfied and
L really is context free, then for
all integers i equal to or greater than 0.
UV to the i, WX to the i, Y is also an L.
We win the game and prove L is not
context-free by allowing the adversaries
choices of n and the breakup of z
subject to the constraints one and two.
And then picking an I such that UV to
the i a WX to the i Y is not an L.
The proof of the pumping Lemma for
context relanguages starts with
the Tromsky normal form grammar for L.
Technically it is for L minus epsilon but
the empty string will never be in the
condition of being of length at least n so
it's presence or absence doesn't matter.
The CNF grammar has invariable's for
some m.
So we're going to let n be 2 to the m.
And now let's consider any strings z and
l of length at least n,
that's 2 to the m again.
We're going to prove first that any
parse tree in a CNF grammar for
string z of length at
least n equals 2 to the m.
Must have a path of length m plus 2 or
more, from the root to a leaf.
We'll actually prove the contra positive,
that is,
suppose there's a parse tree z,
with no path longer than m plus 1.
Such a path as m nodes, labelled by
variables at the top, or the beginning.
And one node labelled by a terminal at
the end, that is, here is a typical path.
It will have variables here, here,
and here and then a terminal there.
Okay, if we forget about
the terminals at the leaves,
a parse tree in the CNF
grammar is a binary tree.
Thus at each level the number
of nodes can at most double.
Thus there is only one node
at the top level, the root,
and there can be only two nodes at
the next level, four at the third,
and, and eight at the fourth, and so on.
In general, there will be at most two of 2
to the power m minus 1 at the nth level.
But this tree has at most
m levels with variables.
And then along each path of variables,
the last variable has one child
with a terminal as its label.
The largest number of leaves
occur if all the paths in
the tree have exactly m variables.
If some paths determinate before
level m there will be fewer leaves.
Thus there are at most two to the m
minus one nodes that are labeled by
variables and
have a single child with a terminal label.
And thus there are at most 2 to the m
minus 1 nodes that
are labeled by variables and
has a single with a terminal label and
thus they are 2 to the m minus 1 leaves.
Finally, we therefore can conclude
that the length of the yield is at
most 2 to the m minus power m minus 1.
Now 2 of the power m minus 1 is n over 2.
Since z is of length n it can not
be the yield of any tree that had
paths limited to length m plus 1 or less.
Therefore we conclude that
somewhere on the parse tree for
z is a length of at least m plus 2.
Now we're ready to proof
the pumping lemma.
We just proved that z's parse tree
has a length of at least m+2.
Only the last node in any path
can be labeled by a terminal so
there are at least m+1 nodes
with variables along this path.
[SOUND] Let's focus on one of the longest
paths in the parse tree for z.
Surely there are at least m+1
variables along this longest path.
[SOUND] Remember that m is the number
of variables of the grammar.
So along this path there are two low nodes
labeled by the same variable,l call it A.
In fact,
to make sure we pump short pieces,
let's look only at the bottommost m
plus one variables along this path,
which could be much
longer than m plus one.
And we know that two of
them must be the same.
[SOUND] On the next slide we'll see
what the parse tree must look like.
Here's a picture of the parse tree for z.
We've show the path we're focused on, and
the lowest competing
variables along that path.
The purple tree is rooted at the lower A,
and the yellow tree with the purple tree
within it, is rooted at the upper A.
The W be the yield with the purple.
Tree.
V and x are the portions of the yield
of the yellow tree that precede and
follow W respectively.
And let u and y be the portions of z that
precede v and follow x respectively.
Let's look at the yellow.
Since the path shown is
as long as any other.
And that path has at most m+1 variables.
We know by the lemma 1
that we just proved,
that the yield of the yellow plus purple
is no longer than 2 to the power m, or n.
That is, the length of VWX is no more
than n.But V and X both can't be empty.
Why?
That's a useful property of kind of,
the Chomsky normal form grammars.
Since the two A's shown in
the tree are different nodes,
the upper A must have a child to
the left or right of the path shown.
That's a consequence of the fact that
we eliminated unit production so
all bodies that have variables.
Have at least two of them.
Moreover, once we have a variable autonoma
path there are no epsilon productions so
we must generate from this
variable at least one terminal.
That is all we need to
conclude that either V or X or
both have length at least one.
Now we can take advantage of the fact
that we have two A's along the path,
we can get rid.
Of v and x by pumping zero times, that is,
we know the purple tree can substitute for
the yellow, because both trees have
the same variable, a, at the root.
If the original on the left satisfies
the conditions of a parsed tree, that is,
every interior node is the head of
a production whose body is the labels of
its children.
Then the same will be true of
the smaller parse tree on the right.
We conclude that u, w,
y is also in the language.
Or we could pump twice.
That is replace the purple tree by the
yellow, which has the purple within it.
And you get a parse tree whose yield is u,
v, v, w, x, x, y.
And in the previous tree representing
pumping twice we could again
replace the purple tree by the yellow and
get a bigger tree whose yield is u,
three v's, w, three x's, and then y.
In the same manner we
can get parse trees for
all strings with the form u, v to the i.
iwx the iy for any integer i equal to or
greater than zero.
These strings are therefore
all in the language L.
That proves the pumping lemma for
context free languages.
Let's look at an example of
how the pumping lemma can be
used to show a language
not to be context free.
This language which involves
matching the counts of two blocks of
zeros is context free.
A grammar or PDA for
it is easy to construct.
The idea is very much like what we saw for
the line of zero to the n, one to the n.
But give the language
three blocks of zeros,
all of which must be the same length.
And we're suddenly outside what
context three grammars can do.
We can prove that using the pumping
lemma for context free languages.
So I'll pick this language, L, and
the adversary now gets to pick N.
We don't know N, but we do know it
is fixed for the rest of the game.
We get to pick Z so let's pick zero to the
N one, zero to the N n one zero to the n.
That is each block of zeros is of length
equal to whatever n the adversary picked.
Now the adversary gets to break
our z up into z equals uvwxy.
But it must choose these substrings such
that vwx together are no longer than n.
And v and x cannot both be
picked to be the empty string.
There are two cases depending upon
whether the adversary picks v and
x to have zeros or not.
In the first case suppose there
are no zeros among v and x.
And since they cannot both be empty
there must be at least one 1 among.
But then if we pump zero
times to get the string uwy,
we know that there is at
most one 1 in this string.
The pumping lemma claims it
is in the language L, but
it can't be because all strings
in L have exactly two 1s.
In the second and last case,
v and x have at least one 0.
Vwx has length at most n, so these three
substrings cannot extend from the first
block of zeros to the last, because
n+2 positions separate those blocks.
So again consider uwy which if l
is context free, he must be in l.
Removing vnx must leave at least one
of the three blocks of n 0's intact so
it still has n 0's.
But vnx have at least one 0,
so in uwy at least one of
the blocks of 0's has fewer than n.
N zeroes.
We conclude that in this case too,
uwy cannot be an L, and
thus L cannot be context free.