Now were going to see more
undecidable problems.
We begin with Rice's theorem which tells
us that almost every question we can
ask about the recursively enumerable
language is as undecidable.
And we then introduce a problem
called Post's Correspondence Problem.
Which we also show is undecidable.
Post problem does not appear to have
anything to do with Turing machine.
So the fact that we can show it is
undecidable is a valuable step on
our road to it showing
real problems undecidable.
However post problem is still a just a
game but, we can use post problems to show
some real problems, for example questions
about grammars to be undecidable.
Well first, see Rice's theorem.
That theorem involves what
are called properties of languages.
Formally a properly of language
is any set of languages.
The languages that we
say have this property.
For example a property of being infinite
is the set of infinite languages.
The property of being empty is the set
containing only the empty language.
While properties like being
infinite apply to any language,
even not recursively enumerable ones,
we need to represent languages, and
the Turing machine is the most powerful
tool we have for representing languages.
So we'll talk about properties of
recursively and enumerable languages only.
So we should consider our property to
be a problem about Turing machines.
Given a code for Turing machine, does it
define a language with that property?
So for any property p,
we can define a language else of p.
The set of binary strings that
represent a Turing machine whose
language has the property p.
So for example, else of infinite,
is the set of codes of Turing machines
that define an infinite language.
There are two properties we call trivial
for reasons that will be obvious.
For this two properties P,
L sub P is decidable.
One of these trivial properties is
the always false property that contains no
recursively enumerable languages.
We can think of this property as, is not
a recursively a enumerable language.
This property is actually
true of some languages, but
those are outside the recursively
enumerable class obviously, and we're
talking about property only as applied
to the recursive enumerable languages.
How do we deci, decide this property?
Given an input w, ignore it and say no.
Notice that even if w represents
an invalid Turing machine code,
we've agreed to take all those strings
as representing a Turing machine that
accepts the empty language.
But the empty language is
a recursive enumerable language, so
we're correct in saying that w's Turing
machine does not have this property.
The second trivial property
is the always-true property.
We can express the property as,
is a recursively enumerable language.
The algorithm for this property is
to ignore the input and say yes.
And Rice's Theorem says,
for every property P,
except the two trivial ones,
else of P is undecidable.
An important part of the proof of Rice's
Theorem, which we'll be working on for
a while, is the idea of a reduction.
There are actually several
different notions of reduction.
We'll come back to that point later.
But the simplest one, and the one we need
for Rice's theorem is an algorithm that
takes and inputs string w for
one language, or a problem L, and
converts it to another string x that
is an input to another language or
problem L prime, with the property that x
is in L prime if and only if w is in L.
The value of having such a reduction
is that it tells us L is
no harder than L prime, at least as
far as decidability is concerned.
If I know L prime is
recursively enumerable, and
I also have a Turing machine program for
L.
If I know L prime is recursive,
then I also have an algorithm for L.
In either case, the solution for L is to
take the input W, convert it to X, see
what the Turing machine for L prime does,
and take it's output to be at answer 4W.
The thing that turns a string W
into X is called a transducer.
So far we've only talked about a Turing
machine whose output is the yes or
a no that is implied by accepting or
halting without accepting, respectively.
But we can get other kinds of output
from a multi tape Turing machine if we
designate one of its tapes
to be the output tape, and
regard what is written there when
the machine halts as its output.
We could, for example,
imagine such a transduce that takes w
on it's input tape and writes x on
its output tape and then halts.
So if we reduce language L to L prime,
using such a transducer and
L prime is decidable, that is, there is an
algorithm to test membership in L prime,
then there is also an algorithm for L.
That is, we start by applying
the transducer to input w,
and producing output x.
We apply the algorithm for
L prime to input x, and decide whether or
not x is in L prime.
Either way, the algorithm render,
renders a decision, either yes or now.
And these two steps form an algorithm for
L.
The whole thing takes input W and
tells us whether or not W is in L.
We sometimes see a reduction used
to discover an algorithm for L.
But the more important use of
the idea's in the contrapositive.
If we already know that
there is no algorithm for
L, then there cannot be any algorithm for
L prime.
That's how we're going to use reductions.
We'll take one problem that we
may not be interested in, but
that we know in undecidable, and
reduce it to another problem that
we are really interested in, but
whose status we don't yet know.
And then we will conclude that
the second problem is also undecidable.
Moreover, when we get to contractability
of the theory of MP completeness,
we'll be using reductions that are fast to
argue that a problem like L prime can't be
solved faster than the problem L.
There are more powerful forms of reduction
that let us reach the same conclusion,
that is if there is an algorithm for
L prime, then there is an algorithm for L.
We actually saw one example of
a more complex reduction when we
started by assuming there was
an algorithm for L sub U.
The universal language.
And showed how we can then
construct an algorithm for
LD which we know does not exist.
However, the hypothetical
algorithm we construct for
L sub D involve more than just
turning one string into another.
We first have to check whether
the input W is a well-formed coal for
a Turing machine, and
if not we answer the question directly.
Morev, moreover, after doing
a transduction where we turn input W
into W111W,
we had to complement the answer that we
got from the hypothetical algorithm for
L sub U.
That is, we turned a yes
answer into no and vice versa.
In the simple version of reduction, we are
not allowed to modify answers in this way.
We have to take whatever answer we get.
We'll revisit this issue of more
general kinds of reductions when we
talk about empty completeness.
There, the simple reduction
is called a Karp reduction.
And more general kinds of reductions
are called Cook reductions.
Steve Cook and Richard Karp, by the way,
were the people who made the earliest
contributions to NP completeness theory.
We're now ready to prove Rice's theorem.
The idea is that we can reduce L sub U to
L sub P for any nontrivial property P.
Then, since we know L
sub U is undecidable,
it follows that L sub P is undecidable.
Here's how we reduce LU to LP.
The input to LU is a Turing machine M and
an input W for M.
The output will be the code for
Turing machine M prime.
That is at least the right form since
LP is a set of Turing machine codes,
those for which the language
of the machine has property P.
Of course, for the transduction from M and
W to M prime to work,
we must arrange that M prime has
property P if and only if M accepts W.
That is M prime is an L sub P,
if and only if M and W is an L sub U.
We'll design M prime to
be a two tape machine.
On the first tape, M prime simulates
another particular Turing machine which
we'll call M sub L on its own input say X.
On the second tape M
prime simulates M on w.
It is important to understand that
M prime has only it's own input x,
which the transducer does not deal with or
see.
The transducer knows about M sub L, it is
built into the design of the transducer.
The transducer gets to see the code for
M and the string W.
That is on it's own input.
Thus, the transducer can build both
the moves of M and the input W
into the transition function of the
machine M prime that is it's own output.
None of M, M of L or
W is input to M prime.
We're going to assume that the empty
language does not have property P.
If that is not the case,
then consider the complement of P say Q.
Surely, the empty language
then has property Q, but
if we could prove that Q are undecidable,
then P also must be undecidable.
That is if LP were a recursive language,
then so
would be LQ since the classic recursive
languages is closed into complementation.
So, let L be any language with property P.
We know L exists because P is not trivial.
Also, let M sub L be the Turing
machine that accepts L.
Here's how M prime behaves.
To begin,
M primes write w on its second tape.
It can do that because the transducer's
seen w generates a sequence of
states that write w one bit at a time.
M prime, from its start state,
enters each of these states in turn.
Then M prime moves the tape head for
tape 2 to the left end, goes to the start
state of M and simulates w on input w.
Again, M prime can do that because
the transducer sees both M and W and
makes the transition function of M part
of the transition function of M prime.
Suppose during the simulation of M on w,
M enters an accepting state.
Then M prime goes to the start
state of M sub L, and
simulates M sub L on
the input x to M prime.
Which has been just sitting there
on tape one, being ignored so far.
Where does M prime get
the transition function for M sub L?
M sub L has a particular Turing machine,
one that accepts a language
L with property p.
Thus the transducer itself can be designed
so that it writes the transitions of M
sub L out as part of the transition
function of M prime.
If M sub L accepts the input x, then M
prime enters in the accepting state.
If M sub L never accepts x,
neither does M prime.
Thus if M prime ever gets to
the stage where it simulates M,
M sub L, then M prime accepts the same
languages M sub L does, that is L.
But if M does not accept W,
then M prime never gets to
the stage where it simulates M sub L,
and therefore M prime accepts nothing.
Here's a picture to help us
remember what M prime does.
It first simulates M on input w.
So far, M prime's own input x is ignored.
But if M accepts w, then M prime
simulates M sub L on its own input x.
And M prime accepts x if and
only if, x is in L.
So, to summarize what
we know about M prime.
First, suppose M accepts w.
Then M prime simulates M sub L on x,
and accepts x if and only if x is in L.
That is, if M accepts w,
then the language of M prime is L.
We know L has property P,
so M prime is in LP.
Now look at the opposite case
where M does not accept w.
An M prime never even starts
the simulation of ML and
therefore M prime cannot
accept its input x.
That is, in this case, the language
of M prime is the empty language.
We know the empty language
does not have property P.
Thus, if M does not accept w,
M prime is not in the language Lp.
We conclude the algorithm we describe for
converting M and w to M prime
as reduction of L subued to Lp.
And therefore that Lp is undecidable.
That is Rice's theorem.
This is a picture that
reviews the argument for
why the existence of the reduction from
Lu to Lp, proves Lp is undecidable.
We have a real reduction algorithm.
I hope you are convinced that you
could program this algorithm if
you were paid enough.
We then, contradict the hypothesis
that Lp has an algorithm by
supposing that algorithm existed.
Then, you could put together the reduction
plus the hypothetical algorithm to build
an algorithm for Lu.
Since we already proved that
there is no such thing,
we have to look at what,
of this story hasn't been proved.
The finger points at
the hypothetical algorithm for
LP, since we didn't prove it exists,
we just assumed it did.
Thus, the assumption must be responsible
for the false conclusion and
we can conclude instead that there
is no algorithm for property P.
Thanks to Rice's theorem,
we suddenly have an infinite collection of
undecidable problems about the languages
defined by Turing machines.
Here is just a tiny sample of
the questions that are undecidable about
Turing machines M.
Is M's language regular?
Or is it context free?
Does this language include at least
one string that is a palindrome?
That is a string that is
the same as its reversal.
Is the language empty?
That is, does M accept any string at all.
Does the language contain
at least 1,000 strings?
But Rice's theorem also applies to
programs since you can write a program to
simulate a Turing machine.
That tells us any non-trivial
question about what a program does
will also be undecidable.
I want to emphasize about
what a program does.
There are lots of questions about other
program it looks like, that are decidable
for example I can tell whether a program
uses more than 20 variable names.
But that's not a question
about what the program does.
An example of a question
about what a program does,
is does the program eventually hole up,
hope on any input?
That is undecidable.
Or does the program
correctly sort its input?
That's undecidable.
Or does this line of
code ever get executed?
That's undecidable.
We're now going to take
Post's Correspondence Problem,
affectionately known as PCP.
PCP is the first example of
a problem that is undecidable, yet
doesn't involve Turing machines or
programs, which are really the same thing.
As we've said,
PCP is not really important by itself,
since it's just a made up problem.
But it leads us to proofs that many
other problems are undecidable.
These problems are unrelated
to Turing machines, but
are related to matters like context free
languages that were not developed for
the purpose of exposing on
this side of the problems.
That is, we studied grammars for
their use in matters like describing
the structure of programming languages.
We had no intent to describe problems
that turned out to be undecidable.
Just turned out that there were
undecidable problems lurking in
the theory of context free grammars.
An instance of PCP is a list
of corresponding strings.
That is a list of pairs of strings
over some particular alphabet sigma.
The instance has some
number of pairs say N.
The first pair is W1 X1,
the second is W2 X2, and so on.
None of the strings can
be the empty string.
The property of the list that makes
the answer to this instance of PCP be yes,
is that when we take the first component
from each pair on the list that is,
WI1 is actually the first component
of the pair that we indexed as i sub 1,
I can't draw on this slide,
two levels of subscripts.
Then w, the second w i2 is the, that w.
From this list that has, in the,
i that's from the i tooth
pair on that list, and so on.
Then, we get the same string if
we take the W's from the pairs,
as if we took the second components or
the X's from the pairs.
Okay?
Such a list of integers is called
a solution to the instance of PCP.
Here is a simple example instance of PCP.
The alphabet will be 0 and 1.
And there are two pairs.
The first pair is 0 and 01.
The second pair is 100 and 001.
Okay, every time a list of integers has 1,
it refers to this pair.
And every time it has a 2,
it refers to that pair.
Okay?
In this case,
it turns out there is no
solution to this instance of PCP.
The analysis of this simple
instance is not so easy.
The easy part is that no solution
can start with the second pair.
Why?
The reason is that if we choose 2 as
the first integer in
the so-called solution list,
then the first string made from
the W's that are first component.
Will begin with this 1.
But the second string, the one made
from the corresponding xs that
are the second components,
begins with a 0.
I don't care how you continue,
a string that begins with 1 can never
equal a string that begins with a 0.
However, it is possible that the solution
list begins at index 1, because repair 1,
the two strings are not inconsistent.
That is, 1 is a prefix of the other.
So, let's see if we can build a solution
starting with the first pair.
Since the two strings are not equal,
we have to add another pair.
We can't choose pair one,
because the first string would then begin
00 and the second string would begin 01.
That could never lead to a solution.
So, the second index in
the solution must be 2.
Now, both strings begin with 0100, and
the second string has an additional 1.
We're back where we were
at the previous choice.
We can't pick 1 as the third index, but
we can pick 2 and we get a match up to
a point with the second string,
again, having an additional 1.
If you think about it,
we can never make the two strings
be the same, because to do so we
would eventually have to use a pair of the
second string was shorter than the first.
But there is no such
pair in this instance.
We conclude that this
instance has answer no.
On the other hand,
let's change the instance a little
by adding a third pair, 110 and 10.
Now the list of indexes 1,
3 is a solution.
From the first strings with the pairs,
we get 0 followed by 110, which is 0110,
that is 0110 is a 0, followed by a 110.
From the corresponding second strings,
we get 01.
That's this, followed by 10.
That's that.
And that also is 0110.
In fact, there is an infinity
of solutions for this instance.
Any string of index is in the language
on regular expression 12 star 3.
That is, after the one,
we can use pair 2 any number of times,
including zero, obviously.
And finally use the pair three.
So, here's the plan for
proving PCP is undecidable.
We're going to start by introducing
a modified version of the problem called
MPCP, or
the modified post correspondence problem.
The modifications is that a solutions to
MPCP must begin with the first pair, but
otherwise the modified and
original PCP problems are the same.
We'll show how to reduce L sub U,
the universal touring machine language to
MPCP, and
then we'll show how to reduce MPCP to PCP.
In fact,
this part is easier to we'll do it first.
Just to get the distinction
between PCP and MPCP clearer,
observe that if we treat the list of three
pairs, from our previous example of PCP,
as an instance of MPCP,
then the answer is yes.
The reason is that there's a sequence
of indexes beginning with one.
Say, 1 3 that produces equal
strings from the first and
second components of the pairs.
But we can reorder the pairs,
say by putting 110 and 10 first.
As an instance of PCP, order of pairs
doesn't matter, there is still a solution.
But as an instance of MPCP,
there is now no solution.
Any solution would have
to begin with index 1.
But then the first of the two
strings would begin 110, and
the second would begin 10.
So no matter how we extend these strings
they disagree in their second positions.
And so they are not equal.
Before we can talk about reductions,
we need to express PCP and
then MPCP as languages.
[SOUND] The instances of these
problems can have any alphabet.
So, it is not immediately obvious
how to express [SOUND] the set of
all PCP instances that have a solution.
Again, the problem is, is there is
no finite alphabet for this set, and
language is just need
to find that alphabet.
So, we need to code symbols
in a finite alphabet.
We'll represent the odd symbol of
an alphabet by the symbol A followed
by I in binary.
Thus we only need three symbols
to represent any number symbols.
The order of symbols of
the alphabet is not important,.
For example if we have an instance
over alphabet A through Z,
we could represent A by a1,
B by a10 and so on.
But we could also represent Z by a1.
And Y by a10, and so on.
It should be clear that
the particular symbols used for
the alphabet of a PCP instance
does not affect the outcome.
And the only other symbols we need to
represent instances are the comma, and
left and right parentheses.
Thus, the alphabet for
the la, language of PCP instances
will have an alphabet of six symbols.
The a, 0, 1, comma,
left paren, and right paren.
Now that we have a finite alphabet for
coding instances,
we can define two languages.
L sub PCP, the language of coded instances
of PCP that have a solution, and
L sub MPCP is the same for
the modified problem.
Now, we can do the reduction
of MPCP to PCP.
We'll describe the transformation only,
but you should be able to
visualize the process being performed
by a trolling machine transducer.
Our input is an instance of MPCP.
The output instance of PCP will use
the same alphabet as the input instance,
plus two new symbols the star and
the dollar sign.
Of course all symbols, the new ones and
the symbols in the input instance of
MPCP will be coded using a zero's and,
ones as we just described.
For each pair WX in the input instance,
there is a pair in the output
instance based on W and X.
For every first string W of the pair,
we add star after every symbol.
So, for example,
01 becomes 0 star, 1 star.
And for X,
the second string of the pair, we instead
add a star before every character.
So, for example,
11 becomes star 1, star 1.
[SOUND] The output instance also has
a new pair unrelated to any input pair.
This pair is dollar sign
paired with star dollar sign.
And the output also has a second
pair based on the first input pair.
This pair has stars placed after
the symbols of the first string, and
before the symbols of the second string.
Just like in rules one and
two on the slide.
But the first string also
has a star at the beginning.
So, for example, the pair 01,
paired with 0, would become star 0 star,
1 star paired with star 0.
Here's an example.
On the left is the instance of MPCP
that is input to the transducer.
On the right are those
pairs with the added stars.
Notice that for each pair the stars come
after the symbols in the first string,
and before the symbols
in the second string.
And, we always add this pair which
will serve to make the strings of
the PCP instance match, when there
is a solution to the MPCP instance.
It's job is to add the missing
start of the second string.
And this pairs would
come from the first pair.
It is just like the first pair
of the PCP instance, except for
the star at the beginning
of the first sting.
Notice that this is the only pair on
the entire PCP instance where both string
start with the same symbol, for
example, this pair has 0 as the first
symbol of the first string and star as
the first symbol of the second string.
Okay.
All these pairs have second strings that
begin with star and
a first string that begins with 0 or 1.
Suppose the MPCP instance has a solution.
A sequence of indexes that yields string
W, when we use the first strings in
the pairs and same string W
when we use the second strings.
Then we can get a solution to
the destructive PC instance.
In this case,
the solution string will be W padded
with stars before each symbol of W.
And also at the end followed
by the dollar sign.
For example,
if W is 101,
then PCP instances solution is
star 1 star 0 star 1 star dollar sign.
To get the PCP solution,
we use the same sequence of indexes,
as in the solution to the MPCP instance,
with two exceptions.
First, we use the index with
the special pair as the first index.
Recall this pair was constructed from
the first pair of the MPCP instance,
with the extra star.
And we also add to the solution of
the PCP for instance the index of
the ender pair star dollar, and
dollar to the end of the list of indexes.
Thus, a solution to the input
MCP instance means that
the output PCP instance
also has a solution.
But the other direction also holds.
If the PCP instance has a solution,
we can modify it to get a solution for
the input MPCP insta, instance.
The first index in the PCP solution
must be the special pair, because that's
the only pair of the PCP instance where
both strings start with the same symbol.
Change this index to 1, the index of
the first pair of the MPCP index.
[SOUND] Leave all the other
indexes unchanged, but remove from
the PCP solution the last index,
which must be the index of the ender pair.
Why?
That's the only pair where both
strings end with the same symbol.
Thus we've shown that the answer to the
questions, does the input MPCP instance
have a solution and does the output PCP
instance have a solution are the same.
That means we have a valid
reduction from MPCP to PCP.
If we can prove MPCP is undecidable.
Which we'll do next.
And we have a proof that
PCP is also undecidable.
So, our next task is to show
how to reduce L sub U to MPCP.
Given as instance, M and W.
Of l sub u will convert this
to an instance of MPCP,
who's only possible
solutions yield strings that
represent the sequence of ID's that
M enters when it's input is W.
More precisely suppose,
this sequence is a sequence of
ID's that M enters starting
with the initial ID of input W.
Then any solution to the constructed
MPCP instance will yield a pair of
strings that begin with the sequence
of ID's, separated by pound signs.
[SOUND] However,
until M enters an accepting state.
When we look at the 2 strings with the
partial solution, one form from the first
string of the index pairs, and the second
from the second string with the index
pairs, the second string will always
be a full ID ahead of the first string.
Only if M accepts,
will we be able to choose pairs that
make the first string grow
faster than the second, and
eventually make the two
strings become identical.
Were going to assume as we can that
the Turing machine M from the input to L
sub U, has a semi infinite tape and never
moves left from the initial head position.
That is, given the actual
binary string representing M,
we can modify the represented machine
to mark its left hand of tape,.
As we did when we describe
the construction of
a Turing machine with a semi-infinite tape
from one that had a two infinite tape.
Then we can perform the reduction
on the new Turing machine that we
know does the same as M,
rather than on M itself.
However, in what follows, we will continue
to refer to the input machine as M.
The MPCP instance we construct will
have an alphabet that consists of
all the states and tape symbols of M,
or rather the modified M,
plus the special marker pound sign.
We assume the symbol is used for state and
tape symbols at this point, so
we can tell one from another in the ID.
Here's the beginning of the construction
of the MPCP instance from M and W.
The first pair has a first string that is
just a pound sign, but a second string
that is the entire first ID with input W,
surrounded by pound signs,
note that the transducer gets the CW on
its input so it can generate this pair.
Will add the pair pound sign,
pound sign, and let's just add markers
to end of one ID in the first string at
the same time we add it to
the following ID in the second string.
At pair X, X for every tape symbol X.
This pair let's us add an X to the idea
we're forming in the first string at
the same time we add an X to the next ID,
which is being formed
on the second string.
Of course, in order to make sure that
the strings match, it must be the case
that an X appears as the first
unmatched symbol of the second string.
Recall the second string
is one idea ahead, so
these pairs, in effect, let us copy
the tap of one ID to the next ID, but
prevents us from making changes that
are not justified by a move of them.
Here's a picture of copying IDs.
Suppose we have just reached a point
in the sequence of indexes when
the second string has complete ID,
more than the first string, but
otherwise the strings match.
We can add to the solution we're
constructing with pair AA.
That has the effect of putting the first
symbol of the new ID at the end of
the first string, and also extending
the second string by the same symbol.
As for what we want, since there's no
way this A can change in the next ID.
We can also then add the index
of the pair BB to the solution,
extending the new ID one symbol further.
This might or might not be the right
thing to do, the problem is that,
if the move of M and stay Q with symbol C
is to move left, then the second symbol of
the new ID is the new state,
and B will be the third symbol.
But just because we can choose
the pair BB doesn't mean we have to.
If M is going to move left, there will
be another choice of next index that
simulates the move correctly, and
the sequence where BB is chosen instead
will fail to yield a solution to
the MPCP instance we're constructing.
Now we need to add the pairs
that reflect the moves of M.
For every state Q and tape symbol X,
if the move of M is to the right,
say P, Y, R, we
have a pair in which Q
to the left of X that's
this, can be replaced by
a P to the right of Y.
That correctly reflects the change in ID
that occurs in the rightward move, and
if the move is to the left,
then we have a family of pairs, one for
each symbol Z that could appear
to the left of the state.
Note that we arrange.
But M can never move left
from its initial position, so
there's no possibility that the status at
the left end of the ID if M goes left.
So if the leftward move has tape Q and
symbol X, replaced by state P and
symbol Y.
And for every Z, there is a pair that puts
P to the left of the Z, and
replaces the X by the Y.
One other probability is that,
in the current ID, the state is at
the right end of the ID, scanning
a blank we've never visited before.
If so, the state will actually be
to the left of the pound sign.
Okay, and the pairs are almost the same,
but when constructing the second string,
we should imagine an extra blanket
in front of the pound sign.
The bank, blank is replace by
the new symbol Y, of course.
Following our previous example,
suppose that in state Q, scanning C,
M does indeed move right, going to
state P, and writing E in place of C.
Had M moved left in that situation,
the sequence of pair choices would be
dead in the water, unable to continue.
However, in that case, we could
have chosen not to use the pair BB.
But instead use a pair that incorporated
the left move and handled the B properly.
In this case we have a pair
with QC as the first string, so
we can match the string on the bottom.
It also extends the bottom string with EP,
reflecting a move event.
Once the move's been handled,
we can just match symbol against symbol,
here the pair DD is used, and
once we are at the end of the ID,
we use the pair of pound signs to
separate the IDs, and we're now ready to
continue the sequence of pair choices
that copy the new ID, which is ABEpD.
And, make it change by another move.
But we need some more pairs in the MPCP
instance so that in case M accepts,
we can find a solution.
Not that if M never accepts, then only
the rules given so far can ever be used.
And these can never lead to a solution
because the second string is
always one ID longer than the first.
However, if M enters a final state f,
then it is possible for
the f to, we'll say eat
the neighboring symbols of an ID.
We no longer have real IDs of M,
but it doesn't matter.
We've simulated M enough
to know that M accepts W.
And our only concern then is to make
sure that there is a solution to
the MPC instance based on M and W.
Thus we add to the instance of MPCP.
Pairs XfY,f, fY, f, and Xf,
f for all tape symbols X and Y.
Using these pairs to get the pairs of the
form x, x to copy parts of IDs as we have
done, we eventually get to an ID
that is only in the state of f.
Of course, that isn't an actually ID of M,
but it doesn't matter anymore.
And one more pair,
f pound pound paired with the pound sign,
will end the two strings being formed,
making them the same, and
yielding a solution to the MPCP instance.
So, here's an example where M
has entered the final state f.
And a sequence of choices,
either copying a symbol, or allowing
f to eat the adjacent symbol or symbols,
eventually leads to identical strings.
So here's what it looks like.
Well, we'll just have to copy that A,
but now the f can,
in effect, eat the B and C adjacent to it.
We have to copy the D, we have to copy
the E, we have to copy the pound sign.
Now, the f can eat the A and the D, but
we have to copy the E,
have to copy the pound sign.
Now f doesn't have anything that
it can eat to its left, but
it still will eat the E.
And finally, copy the pound sign and
now f pound, pound paired with
pound makes everything evened up.
And we have our solution.
Now we know that PCP is
undecidable because we
successfully reduced l sub u2
to it's own language m sub PCP.
And we're going to reduce
PCP to the problem,
is a context free grammar ambiguous?
Then, for the first time, we'll have a
undecidable problem that arose naturally.
That is, not because we were looking for
undecidable problems.
Before we can talk about any
problem involving grammars,
we need to find a code for
grammars using a finite alphabet.
Just as we did for PCP.
So to start the encoding of grammars,
let's represent the i-th terminal by
symbol a followed by i in binary.
That may look, like we're thus forgetting
what the actual terminal symbols are,
but since we're interested in ambiguity,
we can rename the terminals any way we
like as long as we don't
name two terminals the same.
And the ambiguity or unambiguity
of the grammar will not change.
Then we'll represent the i-th variable
by capital A, followed by i in binary.
We will assume that A1 is
always the start symbol.
The right arrow between the head and
body of a production will
be represented by itself.
Likewise, the comma
separating productions,
and the symbol epsilon
will represent themselves.
For example, this grammar is
represented by this string, right here.
The bar connecting alternative bodies for
S has been expanded, so
that there are two separate productions.
This represents S goes to 0S1.
And this much represents
S goes to capital A.
Finally, this represents
capital A goes to little c.
Suppose we have a PCP
instance with k pairs.
And let the i-th pair be wi, xi.
We need k index symbols to
represent the numbers of the pairs.
And we'll use a1 through ak.
Which we may choose for the symbols that
do not appear in the PCP instance itself.
Notice that we're going to reducing
an uncoated instance of PCP, so
it can have any alphabet to an uncoded
grammar, which also can have any symbols.
However, the process we describe really
takes place with all the symbols coded in
the manners we have described.
It is easier to follow the construction in
the uncoded form, so that's what we'll do.
The, the list language for
the first half of each pair.
The strings w1 through wk, has a context
free grammar with productions.
A goes to wi capital A little ai.
It also has the same sort of production,
that, but with A omitted from the body.
The latter kind of productions, these,
are used to end the derivations.
All the strings in this language
are some sequence of the Wi's with
repetitions allowed and in any order.
With the corresponding index
symbols following, but in reverse.
For example, here's a derivation.
Okay, A could derive in one step,
let's say WiA, little A1.
And then in more one step, we could use,
let's say, the terminal production for w2.
So we get w1, w2 and then a2, a1.
Notice that the sequences of as is
the reverse of the sequence of ws.
And we can do the same thing with
the second string from each pair.
We'll use variable B, and Xi's in place
of Wi's, but the idea is the same.
The language of strings generated from
A and B, each consist of the concatenation
of strings, either from the Wi's if
it's A, or the Xi's for methods B,
and these were the first or
second components with their pairs.
Their followed by the reverse of the
sequences of index of the pairs from which
these strings came.
Here's an example of a PCP
instance over alphabet AB.
We'll use 1, 2, and
3 and the index symbols.
So the grammar with
start symbol A is this.
For example,
the second pair whose first string is baa,
gives rise to these two productions.
Here's baa with the variable a in
the middle and then 2, which is the index,
and then there's another production that
is the same but without the capital A.
And here is the grammar for the second
strings in the pairs, with start symbol B.
'Kay, as an example, if we choose
the three pairs in order 1, 2, 3,
then there is a derivation
from A that looks like this.
So, A, use the first, choice.
That's this production.
Then we'll use the second choice,
which is this production.
And that gives us abaaA21.
And then we'll use the third pair.
But we want to end it, so
we'll use that production,
and that gives us abaabaa, sorry, bba.
That's that.
And then three, two, one.
We're now ready to show how to
reduce PCP to the Ambiguity Problem.
Given a PCP instance, construct the two
list languages, with variables A for
the first strings of the pairs,
and variable B for
the second strings of the pairs.
Then add the productions S goes to A and
S goes to B.
Of course,
S is the start symbol of the grammar.
We'll show the resulting
grammar is ambiguous if and
only if there is a solution
to this instance of PCP.
But first let's look at an example that
should actually expose how the proof in
general works.
Okay.
Here is the grammar constructed from
the PCP instance that we saw earlier.
It is the sects of A products and
B productions we saw,
plus the two productions for S.
Okay.
Notice there is a solution, 1, 3.
That is, the first pair was aab, and
the third pair was bba with ba.
When we take the first strings of each
pair, we get abba, this followed by that,
and when we take the second strings of
each pair, ab and ba, we also get abba.
And this common string followed
by the index string in reverse,
which is that,
will have two leftmost derivations.
One starting with a, and
the other starting with b.
Here is the derivation starting with a.
And here's the derivation starting with b.
So, here's the proof this construction is
a correct reduction from PCP to ambiguity.
First, suppose the PCP instance
has a solution say represented by
the sequence of index symbols a1 through
ak, note there can be repeat in the,
in the sequence, then w1 through wK
is the same string as x1 through xk.
That's what it means for this, for
this index sequence to be a solution,
then the two left most derivations of
the string that is w1 through wk, or
equivalently it's x1 through xk.
That is followed by ak down to a1.
One starts with s, goes to a, and
the other starts with s goes to b.
For the converse, we're going to show
that if there are the two leftmost
derivations of the string of terminals,
then one must begin s goes to a,
the other must begin s goes to b.
Suppose there are two leftmost
derivations that begin with s goes to a.
Then, we can look at the sequence of
index symbols in the resulting terminal
string in reverse.
And learn exactly the sequence
of productions used.
Except for the last production used,
each should be
the unique a production that generates
the index symbol and has an a in the body.
And the final production would
be the one with the last that is
leftmost index symbol,
and no a in the body.
The same idea worked for
derivations that start with s goes to b.
There can be only one with a given
sequence of index symbols.
Here's an example.
If the derivation starts with s goes to a,
and produces a terminal string
with index sequence 2321.
And here's what the derivation
of pars three has to look like.
Okay.
First of all we start with a.
The first production used must
generate the one at the right end.
And we need to keep the a,
so this is the only choice.
So, we've generated w1,
off to the left of the a.
The next index symbol from the right end
is a 2, so we have to use this production
again, we still need to keep that a there,
because we have more index symbols to go.
Then the third from left index symbol is
3, so this is the production we have to
use, and then the last index symbol is 2,
that is the left most index symbol is 2,
so we're going to get rid of that a and
use this production.
That's the only way we can generate
a string with 2321 at the end and
no other index symbols.
We can prove many things about context
free grammars, to be undecided as well.
But to do so,
we need to show that the complement of
a list language is also context free.
Remember that the complement of a context
free language need not be context free.
But fortunately, these are for the proof,
we find it easier to construct the push
down automaton, in fact, a deterministic
push down automaton, for the complement.
The PDA we construct will start
with a bottom marker on its stack.
At first,
some symbols from the PCP instance,
not indexed symbols, will appear.
The PDA simply pushes them onto the stack.
After the first index symbol arrives,
start checking that the proper
strings appear on the stack.
Back.
That is if we see an index symbol ai,
then check that the proper wi appears
on the stack with the right end of wi
at the top.
The PDA pops all the symbols of wi if so.
Note that we're assuming this is the
complement of the list language based on
the first component.
If it is for the second components,
we'll check that xi appears on
the top of the stack again,
with the right end at the top.
What we seem to be doing is
accepting the list language itself,
rather than the complement.
But I didn't tell you
when the PDA accepts.
In fact, it accepts every input,
which only the exception of when it has
found a string in the list language.
That is, if the input so far with some
sequence of PCP symbols followed by
some sequence of index symbols, and
these sequences are not empty, and
the bottom stack marker is now exposed,
then the PDA does not expect this string.
It will accept any other string
that follows which cannot then
also be a solution to the PCP instance.
Now, we can use the complement like let
La and Lb be the list languages for
the first and second components
of an instance of PCP and let
La complement and
Lb complement be their complements.
Now, all four of these languages
are context free languages.
Let's consider the union of
the complement languages.
This is also a context free language,
by the fact that context free
languages are closed under union.
I [INAUDIBLE] about this union
equals sigma star, where sigma is
the alphabet consisting of all the symbols
used by the languages involved, if and
only if there is no solution
to the PCP instance.
Suppose there were a solution?
Say represented by the index
symbols a1 through an,
then this string,
is not in the complement of La,
and the equal string, this,
is not in the complement of b.
Thus, if there's a solution,
there's a string missing from the union.
Conversely, suppose string y,
an down to a1, let's say this.
Is missing from the union.
That means that y is the string you get
by using indexes a1, through an and
taking the first strings
from the index pairs.
And it's also the strong you get by
doing the same with the second pairs.
That means a1 through an is
a solution to the PCP instance.
We have now reduced PCP to the question
is a given context free language equal to
all strings over its terminal alphabet?
Thus this problem is undecidable.
Here's another undecidable question.
About context free language.
Is the language also a regular language?
We do exactly the same reduction from PCP,
and one direction is easy.
If there's no solution,
then we just showed that the union of
the complement language is a sigma star.
And that's surely a regular language.
But, we also need to show the converse,
that if L, the union of the complement
languages is something other than sigma
star, then it's not a regular language.
Suppose we have a solution
to the PCP instance, and
in particular that x be
the index symbols in reverse.
And that gives you the solution and
let w be the string you get
by using the first string from
each of the index pairs in order.
Or obviously equivalently the second
string from the same pairs.
Now let h be the homomorphism
defined by h of 0 is w,
and h of 1 is x, remember,
l is the union of the complements.
The strings that are not solutions
to the given instance of PCP.
We claim that 0 to the n 1 to the n,
is not an L for any n.
Because if we repeat a solution to
a PCP instance any number of times,
we also get solution to that instance.
However, h of y is in L for any other y.
That is, h of y is not a solution.
This point requires a little though.
First, if y isn't zeroes followed by ones,
then h of y isn't of the right
form to be a solution to PCP.
That is, it will not consist of
pcp instance symbols followed by
index symbols.
But if y consists of n ones proceeded
by a different number of zeroes,
then it can't possibly
represent the solution.
H applied to the n ones gives
a particular sequence of index x symbols.
But we know the PCP instance
symbol that this sequence of
index symbols corresponds to
is h applied to n zeroes.
Therefore it couldn't also be h applied
to a different number of zeroes.
So, if L,
the union of compliments were regular,
then h inverse of L would also do regular.
Because regular languages are closed
under inverse homeomorphisms.
And the compliment of h inverse of
L would be regular because regular
languages are closed and
their complementation.
But this language we just argued is
the set of 0 to the N, 1 to the N.
Such that N is at least 1.
A language we know very
well not to be regular.